Always bringing up the relations between China, the U.S., and Russia.
没事老拿什么中美俄上三朝关系
All sorts of international influence and whatnot.
各种各样的国际的那影响力
What’s the big deal with international politics?
国际政治又怎么样
Using that as a gimmick.
拿这个当这个噱头
Then talking to ordinary people
然后跟普通人去说
about a bunch of things irrelevant to their lives
一大堆跟他们生活无关的东西
First, let me explain
首先啊我先跟大家说
why I dislike being a grand narrative blogger
我为什么讨厌做宏大叙事博主
because grand narratives can make you lose touch with the core of your life
因为宏大叙事它会让你脱离你生活的中心
but today I'm going to be a grand narrative blogger again
但是今天我又要当一回宏大叙事博主
I'll talk about Zelenskyy
我就来讲一讲小泽啊
and his 50-minute ordeal during this negotiation
泽连斯基在这次谈判中的这个50分分钟啊
suffering humiliation
受辱
Finally being forced out of the White House
最后被赶出白宫啊
What a tough journey
多么不容易
I rarely discuss the Russia-Ukraine conflict in my videos.
我从来不怎么在我的视频里边谈俄乌冲突问题
Or the Russian special military operation
或者说俄罗斯特别军事行动
Or the Russia-Ukraine war
或者说俄乌战争
Regardless
无论怎么样啊
My feelings about this war are very complex
我对这场战争的感受是非常的复杂的啊
And it has been a very long time Because I follow him Since the start of this internal conflict in Ukraine I've already started following him. And my stance has been in support of Russia
也是非常的长久的一段时间 因为我关注他啊 从这个乌冬的这个内战开始 就已经开始关注他了啊 而且我的立场呢从这个支持俄罗斯
to sympathizing with Ukraine
到这个同情乌克兰啊
to being completely neutral
到完全到中立啊
It has gone through three changes
他已经是经过了三次的变化
Actually, there's nothing suspicious about it.
其实呢也没有什么奇怪的啊
Because from the beginning
因为我自始至终
I've maintained a Machiavellian philosophy
我保持的是一种马基亚维利主义的哲学啊
That is, if Xiaoze had really taken the time to study it
也就是说如果小泽真的有好好的去看啊
Speaking of the prince,
君主论的话
Just like my followers studying the Prince
就像我的粉丝研究君主论啊
Putting the prince into practice,
实践君主论的话
there might not be so many problems now
可能就不会有现在这么多的问题了啊
Some people say Rongzhen, you are just a social climber
有人说容振你这个人就是一个社达啊
you are just promoting the survival of the fittest
你就是在推行设达的胜者为王啊
the law of the jungle
弱肉强食动物园法则
you are just advocating these Machiavellian tactics
你就是在啊说这些厚黑学的东西错了
Social Darwinism and Machiavellianism
社会达尔文主义跟马基亚维利主义
are two entirely different things. They represent completely different approaches to life. Social Darwinism refers to the application of Darwinian principles to social and economic issues. Human society also operates under the law of the jungle. It's natural for powerful nations to bully weaker ones.
是完全两种事情啊 是完全两种做人策略 是而社达本身就是说社会达尔文主义就是说啊 人类社会也是在弱肉强食当中啊 大国欺负小国应该的啊
There are all sorts of dynamics at play.
各种各样的东西啊
And strong countries eliminate weaker ones as a result.
然后那个那个强国消灭那个作为
This can lead to the extermination of weaker nations.
对弱国进行这个种族灭绝啊
It's only right.
也是应该的
This is called Social Darwinism.
这个叫社会达尔文主义啊
Your superior race will replace the inferior one.
你优秀的种族会取代劣质的种族啊
You should listen to it.
你会听一听
This is somewhat similar to Fascism.
这就跟啊法西斯主义有点像啊
But the characteristic of Machiavellianism isn't its pragmatism.
但是马基亚维利主义的特点不是它功利啊
The feature of Machiavelli isn't about the survival of the fittest.
马架亚维利的特点也不是它弱肉强食
Because the survival of the fittest is inherent in politics.
因为弱肉强食是政治界本身啊
It's a fundamental principle between nations.
国与国之间的一个基本的一个原则
It's a law of physics
就是一个物理定律
the weak are bullied
弱的欺负啊
the weak are bullied by the strong
弱的被强的欺负
the big eating the small is quite normal
大的吃小的很正常
but what is a Machiavellian
但是马基亚维利主义者是什么
Machiavellians primarily deceive others through manipulation
马基亚维利主义者主要是通过骗呵骗对方
Deceiving oneself to ultimately achieve a pragmatic outcome.
骗自己最后达到实用主义效果啊
remember this I admire these historical conspirators Their reputations aren't great Machiavelli Sanada Masayuki Tokugawa Ieyasu Sima Yi
大家记住啊 我崇拜的这些历史上的这些阴谋家啊 名声都不太好 马嘉维利呀 真田昌幸啊 德川家康啊 司马懿啊
Tywin
泰温呐
Jia Xu
贾诩啊
These people
这些人
Remember, these are the ones who can leverage the small to achieve the great
你记住这些人都是会用得最小代大
To achieve the greatest results with the least cost,
对最小的代价去取得最大成果的人啊
If you call me a Machiavellian,
如果你说我是马基亚维利主义者
I’ll clap for you,
我给你鼓鼓掌
If you say I'm a social Darwinist
如果你说我社会达尔文主义
Bro,
我说哥们
You need to read more books.
你多读点书吧
Is that all you can think of, social Darwinism?
你脑子里是不是就只有社达社达
You’re a social Darwinist,
你是社达
You’re a social Darwinist.
你是社达嗯
Is that the only way of thinking?
是不是就只有这种思维啊
Right?
对不对
You should learn a new word, okay?
你就学个新词儿对吧
The mask of ideology
马甲为主义啊
What is it like?
是什么样
This is what I've been trying to explain to you
这是我一直在向你科普的
If Xiao Ze
如果小泽啊
Xiao Zelensky
小泽连斯基
He is a social Darwinist.
他是一个社会达尔文主义者啊
He might not put up any resistance at all
那他可能完完全全就不会做反抗
He wouldn't fight back
不会做抵抗啊
But I still feel a bit sorry for him
但是我还是有点同情他
I even admire him a little
有点佩服他
After all, he was given the task in an emergency situation.
因为他说实在的也算是临危受命啊
He held his ground for so long during the war To start with I think during Poroshenko's era There was this kind of civil war oppression in Eastern Ukraine This is inherently unjust. Russia, from this perspective,
在战争当中硬扛了这么长时间 从最开始来讲 我觉得在波罗申科那个时代 对乌东的进行这种内战压迫 这本身就是不公义的 俄罗斯他作为啊从这方面来讲
the relationship between the protected and the protector,
作为被保护者与保护者之间的关系呢
does have a justification for military intervention.
他是有出兵理由的
But expanding the war to the entire territory of Ukraine,
但是把这个战争扩大到整个乌克兰全境
has led to massive casualties and property damage,
然后又导致了一种大量的人员与财产的损失
which may not have been what Russia truly intended.
这个东西呢其实也未必是俄罗斯真正想这样
But the reality is as it is.
但是现实的结果就是这样
You shouldn't assist a weaker party.
就是你不要去帮助一个弱者啊
Because helping the weak is not the right thing to do.
因为帮助弱者是不对的啊
Helping the weak has never been a right thing to do.
帮助弱者从来就不是一件对事啊
Why is helping the weak not the right thing to do?
为什么帮助弱者是不对的
Because when you help the weak,
因为帮助弱者
they themselves
他本身自己
won't become strong quickly just because of your help.
并不会因为你的帮助而迅速变得强大
Instead, you only make the weak's tragic fate even more tragic.
而你只会让弱者的悲惨命运更悲惨啊
If we think about it,
倘若我们想一下
if no country had helped Ukraine at the beginning
如果当初没有任何国家去帮助乌克兰
No one stood by his side
没有任何人去站在他的一方
Ukraine would quickly fail, right?
乌克兰会迅速失败对吧
Then sign a humiliating peace treaty
然后签下城下之盟
There's a possibility of being completely annexed There's a chance the east could be annexed But is it possible so many people would die? Is it possible to lose so much property? It's not certain that a humiliating peace treaty would be signed
有可能被完全吞并啊 有可能啊被吞并了东部啊 但是呢有可能死现在这么多人吗 啊有可能损失这么多财产啊 未必有可能签了城下之盟
It's possible there wouldn't be so much trouble
有可能就没有这么多事
But all of this is possible
但是这一切都说是有可能
Once a person doesn't resist a force
一旦一个人并没有抵抗一个势力的
Such overwhelming power
强力的这种武力
He ends up possessing these things under others' encouragement
他又在别人的怂恿之下拥有了这些东西
It's like you don't have any weapons yourself
就像你本身你没有武器
You can't fight off a thug, right?
你打不过流氓对吧
But now you've been given a bunch of weapons
然后呢你现在呢被拿出一大堆武器啊
You can take on the thug
你就可以打过流氓了
But the issue is
但是问题就是
The person who gives you a weapon hopes you will defeat the bully
给你武器的人是希望你把流氓打死呢
or does he hope you will perish together with the bully?
还是希望你跟流氓同归于尽呢
That's the question.
这就是一个问题了
Are you the dish on the table?
是你是桌上的菜呢
Or do they act out of a simple sense of heroism,
还是他们出于一种朴素的啊英雄主义情结
a desire to stand up to the strong and help the weak?
一种锄强扶弱的情节
I believe in Europe,
我相信在欧洲
Today's statesmen
今天的政治家
many of them are driven by a desire to stand up to the strong and help the weak.
有很多人都是有锄强扶弱的情结的人啊
This is great.
这样很好
They are idealists.
他们是理想主义者
But the last thing idealists should do is get involved in politics.
但是他们理想主义者最不应该做的就是从政
Because politics is a complex business. Politics demands the most cunning. The most devious. The darkest tactics. And the blackest hearts. There are no moral boundaries whatsoever. A person without any moral restraints going into politics
因为从政这件事情很复杂 从政应该是最狡猾 最阴险啊 手段最黑 然后心最黑 没有任何道德界限 没有任何道德束缚的人去从政
This is the attitude a statesman should have.
这才是政治家应该有的一个态度
The reason I dislike everyone getting into grand narratives is
我之所以不喜欢大家去搞宏大叙事
is because in my limited life experience,
因为在我有限的人生当中
I've come to realize many things.
我认识到很多啊
Our society has a lot of very capable people,
咱们社会当中呢非常有厉害的啊
very talented individuals.
非常有能力的人物
These people,
这些人啊
believe me, in the context of Chinese history,
大家相信我任何在在中国历史上来讲
any exceptionally powerful
任何非常强大的
highly intelligent
非常有头脑的
extremely wise
非常有智慧的
these individuals
这些人
are certainly on the forefront of the nation
一定啊都是在国家这一头
these people have more conscience than I do
这些人比我要有良心啊
more insight than I do
比我要有睿智
more perseverance than I do
比我要有耐力
more strategic resolve than I do
比我要有战略定力
You don't have to go.
你们不用去啊
Don't worry about what I said.
在意我说这事儿
But I will compare you to them.
但是我会拿你们去跟他们去相比
These people,
而这些人啊
the ones who truly decide the future of the country, are not confused at all.
真正决定国家前途命运的这些人一点都不糊涂
And they are not as unscrupulous as I am.
而且他们没有我这么丧良心
So there's no need for you to worry. There's no need to worry. If the world were full of people as unscrupulous as me, If Machiavellians were to control the big picture, let me tell you, the world would become incredibly interesting.
所以你们也没有必要担什么心啊 没有必要担什么心 如果这个世界都是像我这种比较丧良心的 马基亚维主义者来控制这些大局的话 那我跟你说 这个世界会变得非常有意思
Primarily because,
因为主要来讲的话
The mindset of social Darwinists is predatory.
社会达尔文主义的人思维就是啊掠夺式的
aggressive,
进攻式的
while Machiavellians are mainly about deception,
而马基亚维利主义者主要就是骗啊
sneaking attacks and trickery,
搞偷袭骗啊
achieving maximum benefits with minimal costs.
最小的代价获得最大利益
This is the core of being a Marxist.
这才是马建为主义者的核心啊
So, if I were Ozawa, what would I do?
所以说如果我是小泽的话会怎么样
I would tell Vance and Trump this.
我会把万斯跟特朗普说的唉
I would really talk it up, make it sound fantastic.
天花乱坠吹得实在实实在在的
And I would agree to all their demands.
而我会答应他们的一切要求
But at the same time, I would reach out to Russia myself.
但是同时我会自己跟俄罗斯接触
I would also talk it up, make it sound fantastic.
我也会把他们吹得天花乱坠
Then I would agree to all their demands.
然后答应他们的一切要求
The most important thing would be to play one against the other.
然后最重要的就是驱虎吞狼之举
One woman married to two men
一女许二夫
Got it?
明白了吧
I want the original work
原著我要啊
I want military aid
军援我要啊
I need the reconstruction funds, right?
重建经费我要对吧
But you see, I’m negotiating with Russia, and both sides are greedy So let them compete for a mine Sell the same deal to both sides, one woman married to two men Right? The most important thing is what actual benefits I can get.
但是呢你看我跟俄罗斯我也谈两家都贪啊 就让他们去竞争一个矿 卖两家一女许二夫啊 对不对 最重要的就是我实际能获得什么利益
I know you can't keep going now.
我知道你现在也打不下去了
You guys also hope I bleed more, right?
你们现在呢也是希望我多流血啊
Some people want you to bleed more.
有些人是希望你多流血
But in this situation,
但是在这个当中
Actually, those European politicians are the most damn incompetent bunch of people.
其实欧洲这帮政治家是最他妈二逼的一帮人啊
Because whether you're a Machiavellian,
因为无论你是马加维利主义者
Pragmatism
实用主义啊
like Trump.
像特朗普啊
Wan Si
万斯
Actually, they have a typical businessman’s mindset.
其实他们就是典型的商人思维
This mindset is also characteristic of Machiavellianism.
商人思维其实也是马加雷主义者的一个思维
It's not just a form of egoism
就是它不光是一种利己主义
It's more of a philosophy of pragmatism and ethics.
它更多的是一种实用主义哲学道德
Practicality trumps everything else.
为了实用都可以靠边站啊
There’s no morality at all.
完全没有道德
They may talk about ethics,
虽然嘴上称的是道德
but in reality, there’s no morality.
但实际上没有道德
This is a characteristic of Magawist ideology.
这是马加维主义者的特点
These Europeans are idealists.
欧洲这帮人是理想主义啊
I’m the one who will support whoever is invaded.
我就是谁受侵略了
I will offer them support.
我就要支援他
But there’s also a bit of selfishness involved.
他这个其实还有一种小自私的心理
Let them be the ones to die. Let the fighting happen on their territory. It’s better than me having to make any real sacrifices. Right, isn’t it? Then I'll send the troops I'll send military personnel as volunteers I'll send the weapons
让他去死人 让他的领土上作战 总比在我要付出点实际的那什么 好吧对吧 那我就派军队 我就派军人当志愿者 我就派这武器
I'll send all kinds of experts and personnel
我就派各种各样的人员专家去啊
This way, I minimize my losses while inflicting casualties on him
这样我以最小代价死他的人哦
I'll support him morally
我精神上支持他
That's a petty calculation
这是小算盘
Speaking of Russia
俄罗斯来讲
To put it bluntly, it's about not backing down
说白了就是不服
Let's just do it.
咱就他妈干哈
Russia only has two allies.
俄罗斯只有两个盟友
One is the Air Force.
一个是空军
The other is the Navy, right?
一个是海军是吧
The other is the Navy.
一个是海军
One is the Army.
一个是陆军
No matter what.
甭管怎么样啊
Russia is a typical example of this.
俄罗斯是典型的这种
It doesn't have much power now.
现在没有什么实力
Not knowing how to keep a low profile
不会韬光养晦啊
The treasury in Kulun is left with nothing but mouse droppings
库伦那个国库里就剩耗子屎了
And they still wage war recklessly
然后还他妈的穷兵独武
So when we talk about Russia, it’s Russia
所以来讲俄罗斯就是俄罗斯
China is China
中国是中国
China is a country with a 5000-year history of civilization.
中国是一个拥有5000年文明史的
And it’s only been 15 years
而且只有15年啊
The longest period of peace has only been 15 years for this country
最长的和平时期只有15年的一个国家
Our country, the longest period has been roughly that
咱们的国家大概最长啊
How to put it,
怎么说呢
For the most part, we've been at war for thousands of years,
基本上几千年来基本上都在打仗
Peaceful times have been few and far between. But today, we leverage our strategic advantages to replace tactical victories. It's truly a smart and effective move.
基本上都在打和平时期屈指可数啊 但我们今天以战略上的优势来取连 来取代战术上的这种胜利 真的是非常非常聪明好干的
It’s about winning without fighting.
就是不战而屈人之兵啊
This is the pinnacle of Machiavellianism.
这是马驾唯利主义者的高潮
Winning without fighting is the ultimate goal.
就是不战而屈人之兵是最爽的
Ideally, not a single soldier would be lost
最好就是一个兵都不死
yet the issue would be resolved
还把事解决了
and our strength would increase
自己实力还上升
So, in the current situation
所以现在来讲的话
these European countries
欧洲这帮啊
with the ongoing conflict between Russia and Ukraine
俄乌现在打成这个吊样
the U.S. is now building up its military
美国现在建军啊
and has stepped in
插了一杠
This, in turn, affects all these matters
这个来讲是对所有的这些事情来讲
This is the most beneficial for us
是最有利于咱们的
So when you say I'm a social Darwinist
所以来讲你说我是社达
I really don't find it meaningful
我真的是觉得没有什么意义
Because I'm a thorough Machiavellian
因为我是彻彻底底的马基亚维利主义者
Remember, as a Machiavellian
因为马基亚维利主义者记住
You can speak freely
就是你话可以随便说啊
The purpose of speaking is to make the other person happy
说话的目的是为了让对方高兴
It's to gain practical benefits
是为了获得实际的利益
Since Trump can offer you these things
既然特朗普能够给你这些东西
If you can offer something genuine
能够给你真实的东西
you should do a favor for him
你就应该做个人情给他
because you don't have to do what you promised immediately, right? You promised him a mine, didn't you? The mine was taken by Russia, wasn't it? I couldn't defend it so I gave it to you Isn't that right?
因为你答应他的事情不用马上办明白吗 你答应给他矿场哎 矿场被俄罗斯抢走了对吧 我无力防守 我就给你了 对不对
Can a woman be married to two men at the same time?
可以一女许二夫君源
It's real money that's brought back.
拿回来是实实实实在在的钱
To put it bluntly, you need to figure out Trump's mindset.
说白了就是你就琢磨特朗普的思维
He believes that Biden's promises no longer count.
就是他认为拜登许诺的不算了
There's a new person in charge now.
已经换了当家人了
I feel like I'm spending too much now.
我现在觉得花钱多
I don't want to manage things over there anymore.
我现在不想在那边管了
Give Russia a favor.
卖个人情给俄罗斯
I'll just keep harvesting your resources.
我再收割你资源就完了
You know very well that's his plan.
你明知道他就是这个打算
But now you're the pawn
但是你现在你是棋子
You're not the player on the board
你不是棋盘上的棋手
You're just a pawn
你只是棋子
A pawn needs to find ways to be traded as many times as possible
棋子就要想办法把自己卖的尽量多次
Make everyone feel like you're their pawn
让任何人感觉都你是他的棋子
That you're speaking for their interests
你在为他的利益说话
So in many cases
所以很多的时候来讲的话
The cards in his hand are really few
他手里的牌真的是非常少
Trump, to put it bluntly, is making a big sacrifice
特朗普其实说白了他是舍大
He can see these things very clearly.
他能把这些东西看的很明白
You feel like you have no cards left to play.
你觉得没有什么牌可走了
This was the food on the table from the start.
你这本来就是桌上的食物
What leverage do you have for negotiation?
你有什么谈判的权利呢
I’ve been very clear with you.
说的很明白的跟你说了
Since you’re not giving me any face,
既然你不给我面子
I won’t give you any face either.
那我也不给你面子
Actually, you can play alone.
其实可以play play alone
You can pretend to do a better job. You're clearly Zelensky You're an actor But these political actors are much more skilled than you What is the most valuable
可以假装的弄得好一点 你明明泽连斯基 你是个演员 但是政治上的这些演员比你要厉害的多啊 什么东西最有价值
It's the hand that's hard to extend
就是不容易伸出去的手
A hand that's easy to extend is worthless
容易伸出去的手没有价值
You suddenly decide to fly to Moscow to meet Putin
你这时候突然去飞到莫斯科去见普京
Or somehow mediate between them
或者怎么着从中斡旋
That's when you get to the table
这个时候你才上桌
Did you know?
你知道吗
If you go and talk to the U.S. now,
你现在去又跟美国去谈
and then go and talk to Europe,
又跟欧洲去谈
and go and talk to those who are slaves to the slave masters,
又跟那帮女奴才做奴才的奴才去谈
it's they who will provide you with weapons,
是他们会给你武器
it's they who will bear more of the costs,
是他们会承担更多的钱
and then,
然后呢
the war will continue,
这战争继续打
what you truly exhaust is your population resources.
你真正消耗的是拿你的人口资源
Engaging in a resource and population drain with Russia
跟俄罗斯的人口资源相互去耗
None of you have a substantial manpower advantage
你们谁都没有太多的人员的实力
If your demographic structure collapses
你的人口结构一旦崩了的话
Your country ceases to exist
你这国家就不存在了
The territory remains
领土还在
But if the demographic structure collapses
人口结构崩了
You cease to exist as well
你也不存在了
The nation's assets are gone
国家的资产没有了
These countries would no longer exist
你这些国家也不存在了
The country's territory is gone.
国家的领土没有了
Your country no longer exists.
你这国家也不存在了
To put it bluntly, you're now just a piece on the plate.
说白了你现在就是一盘菜
So, from the very beginning, when we talk about it,
所以从一开始当初来讲的话
We're talking about the shift from Ukraine to anti-Russian sentiment. The shift towards ethnic conflict from the start. So, going back to the earliest days of Yushchenko's era, And even further back to the Orange Revolution, regardless of how it played out,
咱们说从乌克兰转向反俄 转向那个民族对抗这一开始 所以说最早的从尤先科那个时代来讲 再往前橙色革命不管怎么也好
So, if you look at Ukraine's history today,
所以从如果你今天再去看乌克兰的历史来讲
He has always been such a figure.
他一直是这么样一个角色
Used back and forth by several major forces.
被几大势力来回来去的用
Let's not talk about Ukraine's early history.
咱们就不说乌克兰早期的历史了啊
Just talking about the Black Army.
就说黑军啊
And the Red Army.
跟这个红军啊
Is there also the White Army?
是不是还有白军
There was a place where four armies—the Blue, Black, Red, and White—clashed.
有蓝军四军交战之地啊
Russia stormed into Crimea.
俄罗斯奔攻克格兰
Regardless of the stance taken by Russia.
你不管斩的是俄罗斯的立场
From the Soviet Union's perspective
站在苏联的立场
or from the standpoint of Ukrainian nationalists
还是站在乌克兰本土的
the issue of Ukraine's shifting alliances
民族主义者的立场来讲的
has also been quite frequent
乌克兰这个临阵易治的这种事啊
which makes its history incredibly complex
也干的是不少
Of course
所以来讲的话他的这个历史非常的复杂
we respect the territorial integrity of all countries
当然来讲
This is a fundamental policy of our country
咱们说咱们尊重一切的国家的领土完整
This is quite normal.
这很正常
But from their perspective,
但是在他们来讲的话
To be honest,
说实在的
they are willing to be used by Europe,
自己是甘心情愿被欧洲
as a pawn in their game.
当一个马前卒去使用的啊
To be honest, I've always thought that Eastern Europeans are not very smart. Most Eastern Europeans are farmers, so there aren't as many big businessmen among them. Great philosophers
说实在的 我一直认为东欧人不够聪明 东欧人农夫啊居多 所以东欧人那么没有那么多的大商人啊 大师哲学家啊
eminent scholars, or how should I put it
大学者甚至是怎么说呢
many of those scientists ended up in Western Europe
那些科学家真的很多人都是到了西欧啊
or in the United States, Berlin, and so on
到了美国柏林斯跟泽连斯啊
not Zelensky
不是泽连斯基啊
Madame Curie and the like
居里夫人啊什么的
many people followed this path
很多人都是这样
or became prominent after living in London
或者旅居伦敦才变得厉害
to be precise
真正来讲
Eastern Europe doesn't produce a lot of such talents.
东欧没有什么产生什么特别多的这种人才
It lacks the environment for that.
因为他没有这种
Maybe it's just my limited experience.
可能是我见识短吧
Anyway, I haven't seen any great statesmen emerge from there.
反正我没有见到那儿出现什么伟大的政治家了
We won't talk about figures like Lenin or Stalin.
反正咱们就不说什么苏勋宗之类的啊
Corn tycoon.
玉米玉米大亨
There are certain things we can discuss about them.
有些东西咱们就是说他的一些东西
Politics requires a certain level of foundation.
政治是要有一个积淀的
What kind of country is likely to produce great statesmen?
什么样的国家容易出大政治家
Russia
俄罗斯啊
the UK and France
英国法国
Germany
德国
the United States
美国
China is prone to producing great statesmen.
中国这样容易出大政治家
Japan rarely produces great statesmen
日本都不一容易出大政治家
because its territory is so limited its mindset its history and available references are also limited So, I want to share with everyone Statesmen who have read The Prince Unlike a statesman who hasn't read The Prince And the common people who have read The Prince
因为他的国土就那么小 他的思维 他的历史他能够参考系就那么多 所以跟大家说 看过君主论的政治家 跟没看过君主论的政治家不一样 而看过君主论的老百姓
become harder to govern
从此就不好被管理了啊
because you understand the essence of politics
因为你就知道政治的本质是怎么回事
the core of politics is often deception
政治的本质主要是欺骗啊
to put it nicely
说好听的
and then they deny what they've done
然后是干了不认死
No reconciliation
无对账
You can sell it to him
你可以卖给他呀
Then you can change your mind
然后你再反悔呀
You can sell him some items
你可以卖给他一些东西
Things he wants
他想要的东西
Then drag it out
然后慢慢拖呀
Then switch to someone else to handle it
然后你这换个人再来干啊
Right?
对不对
The previous government's matters are left undone
前任政府的事就不干了
So he has a lot of options to counter with.
所以其实他有很多可以对抗的东西
Small players have their own methods.
小玩家有小玩家的方法
Big players have a variety of strategies.
大玩家有大玩家的这种各种各样的策略
Right?
对不对
You have so many mine layers to use.
你有那么多布雷车呢用啊
Buy your assets.
买你的资产
OK, I can contaminate it.
OKOK我可以污染它
I can pick up the radioactive materials.
我可以放射性的东西可以拾起来
Is that right?
对不对
There are so many things we can do.
好多东西可以做呢
You can, but I can't.
你可以我用不了
Neither can others.
你也别人也用不了
So, in many cases,
所以很多的时候来讲
Your country has plenty of such harmful tactics. Now, let me tell you, Does Poland have territorial claims against you? Don't other countries have territorial claims against you as well? You take a bit from the east
这损人的招儿多的是你的国家 现在来讲跟你说 波兰跟你有领土需求吗 其他国家难道没跟你有领土需求吗 你对东吃一块
and a bit from the west
西扯一块
and in the end, you find yourself to be nothing
最后你发现你自己什么都不是了
That's why a weak country has no diplomacy
所以说弱国无外交
So we say what Comrade Ozawa did worst
所以我们说小泽同志做的最不对的
was violating the fundamental principles of politics
就是政治的基本原则
He didn't grasp them
他没有掌握啊
In this situation
在这种情况下
not giving face to the ruler of a superior state
不给上国之君面子
This will only lead to more problems.
这事会容起引起更多的问题了
You have so many people.
你有那么多人啊
Think about what you can provide for them.
去想给你去给你去供给给你去什么
But they all dare not provoke the U.S.
但是他们都不敢惹美国啊
Between the U.S. and Russia, you can only follow one.
美美俄之间你只能跟一个大哥
Since you've chosen Russia,
你既然跟了俄罗斯
you have to stand against the U.S.
你就得跟美国
Right?
对不对
You are opposing the U.S. with Russia.
你跟俄罗斯对抗
You should be a bit nicer to the U.S.
你就得跟美国就得稍微好一点
Or do you have another big brother?
要不你还有另外一个大哥呢
Right?
对不对
You have another big brother who has hinted at this multiple times,
你有另外一个大哥多次暗示你
Actually, he can ensure your safety.
其实可以保你一方周全
Seeking help from this big brother is the most effective approach.
你找这个大哥是最管用的
Because he has a good rapport with Russia.
因为他跟俄罗斯说得上话
But you abandoned this strategy.
但是你又放弃了这条策略
You then felt that
你又觉得啊
So, how about that?
那怎么怎么样
Whoever supports me
谁只要支持我
So you're going to support those people on the other side, right? This is where you're being unwise. You haven't fully grasped international politics. Your thinking is too Westernized. You're too Europeanized. You're too Eurocentric.
所以你要去支持对岸的那些人对吧 所以这就是你不明智的地方 你没有把国际政治想明白 你太西方化的思维了 你太欧洲化了 你太欧罗巴了
You're too focused on the world, how to put it...
你太站在世界的怎么说呢
On the side of fairness and justice
公平与正义的那一侧了
The true power of the world is in the hands of the few
世界的真正的力量是在上三场手中的
Above all, it's about strength
实力之上啊
The methods of Shida are absolutely correct
是社达的那套东西绝对没有错
But in international politics, strength prevails
但国际政治上就是实力为上
What comes above strength?
实力之上的是什么呢
It's the intrigues and schemes
就是阴谋诡计
It's all about the vertical and horizontal alliances.
就是各种合纵连横
On the surface, it's just a show
表面上在那突突嘛
Under the bridge, they're secretly tripping people's legs.
桥底下在底下勾人家大腿啊
On the surface, they're shaking hands.
表面上握手
Under the table, they're kicking others' chairs.
下巴里边踹别人的凳子
That's the kind of thing they do.
就是干这种事啊
They say they won't do it.
说了不做
But they do it without saying.
做了不说
They speak sweet words.
说好听的话
But they do the dirtiest deeds.
干最操蛋的事
This is politics.
这就是政治
Speak the softest words
说最软的话
Do the hardest things
干最硬的事
This is politics too
这也是政治啊
Speak the hardest words
说最硬的话
And then do the softest things
然后干最软的事
Bow and apologize behind people's backs
背地地里给人磕头道歉的
This is also politics
这也是政治
So politics is definitely for high-IQ individuals
所以政治这个东西呢一定是高智商的人
Certainly for those who can control their emotions It must be someone who can put aside their pride It must be something only a person without a sense of morality or shame would do In many cases
一定是能够控制情绪的人 一定能是拉下来脸的人 一定能是没有道德羞耻感的人才能做的事情啊 很多时候来讲的话
a person believes
一个人相信啊
you have to deal with many people
你要你很多的那人
I'm unwilling to let them get entangled in grand narratives
我就不愿意让他们陷入宏大叙事的根本原因
because getting entangled in grand narratives for you
是因为从陷入宏大叙事对你来讲
has no practical value in reality
没有现实当中的作用
it has no practical value in reality
他没有现实当中的作用
And your mind
而你的心智
Most of your mind is that of a child
你的大部分心智属于儿童心智啊
It falls under the Peter Pan effect
属于彼得潘效应
Childlike mind
儿童心智
You haven't really grasped the adult world
你并没有真正把成人世界容易看明白
So tolerance is crucial
所以说容忍是社达龙
What exactly is it
真是什么
I see him like my dad
我看他像我爸爸
So that's how it is
所以就是这样
You don't understand what it means to let go.
你不明白什么是舍得
And you really dislike making big sacrifices.
你又很讨厌舍大
Then who can offer you protection?
然后谁能给你保护呢
Who can provide you with crucial help?
谁能给你关键性的帮助呢
So, what about the idealist? What are they supposed to do?
啊理想主义者你又怎么办呢
Can you solve most of the world's problems?
你能解决了世界上大部分事情吗
Can you stand up to the punk?
你干得过黄毛吗
Can you stand up to your neighbor Old Wang?
干得过隔壁老王吗
Can you stand up to the thugs with thick arms and legs?
你干得过胳膊大腿粗的流氓吗
You can't outdo it
你干不过
So, when talking about it if you truly want to possess wisdom if you want to take down the giant you have to embrace Marxist ideology What is Marxist ideology? start by studying it thoroughly First, read through 'the prince' thoroughly.
所以来讲的话 真正你要想拥有智慧 想干掉硕大 就得拥抱马价为主义 马价为主义是什么 先好好去研究一下 先好好的把君主论通读一遍
don't always rely on your Peter Pan effect
不要老用自己的彼得潘效应
That post-adolescent, postmodern sense of self-respect
那点儿青春期后置的后现代的那种自尊心
The naive, romantic idealism of a bohemian
文艺青年那种傻的天真浪漫
Coupled with the foolishness of an idealist
加上理想主义者的那个白痴
Thinking you can also play politics
他妈的也要当政的感觉
Don't do this kind of thing
不要干这种事啊
Don't do this
不要干这种事
Politics isn't a game for you brain-dead people
政治不是给你们这帮脑残玩的吧
There are truly smart
真正聪明
Truly ruthless, people who are blacker than their faces
真正心黑心比脸黑的人有的是啊
You have to believe that in our vast country
你要相信我在咱们这个广袤国土上
there are all kinds of powerful talents
什么样强力的人才都有
and these people have been working behind the scenes
而这些人早就暗中的啊
How should I put it
怎么说呢
Well, let me think
就是不用替你们去
there's no need to worry on behalf of everyone
不用替大家去担心啊
You think it's a good thing, don't you
你觉得啊好事啊
but I'm not part of this wise think tank
这个智慧智囊里边没有我啊
What should we do about this?
这个怎么办啊
Without me, this country wouldn't be able to function, would it?
没有我这个这个国家不就不行了吗
Don't worry.
你放心
There are people much more capable than you.
有比你强力的多的人
They've already started making their moves long ago. So you don't need to worry. I'm just the one who came out to say these things. I'm just a small cameo in 'Color Me'. But I have to break this down.
都早就啊咋开始布局了 所以你不用担心 我出来讲这些的人 只不过是color me中的小卡拉咪啊 但是我要必须要把这东西掰开了
Let me break it down for you.
揉碎跟你讲
First of all, there's nothing to worry about.
因为首先没有什么可要担心的
We are a major player in this matter.
咱们首先在这件事情上是一个大的玩家
And our pandas, for instance,
而我们这些熊猫啊
to be honest, the rabbits,
兔子说实在的
in this regard,
在这方面来讲
are extremely capable.
能力是非常非常强的
We are a country with strategic resolve.
咱们是明白有战略定力的国家
We also have the tactical power to destroy anything.
也有战术上能够毁灭一切的力量啊
We have the authority for decisive air combat.
有空战的决战权的
Now, I'm being serious.
现在是不开玩笑
Whether it's strategic or tactical weapons,
甭管是战略武器还是战术武器
or conventional weapons,
还是常规武器
Conventional,
Conventional
Unconventional walls,
Unconventional wall
We can win in all scenarios.
咱们都是可以赢的
And we've always relied on everyone's support.
而且咱们的一直赖着大家呢
Our stance is clear: we're ready to take on the world, plain and simple.
咱们的定调就是单挑全世界就这么简单
This is no exaggeration.
这一点都不夸张
So, in many cases,
所以很多的时候来讲的话
the competition and rivalry between major powers
咱们一些大国之间的竞争较量
is entirely different from that with smaller countries.
跟小国是完全不一样
We don't need to take sides.
咱们不用站队
Because if we do,
因为咱们站队了
the other side wins.
那边就赢了
It's that simple.
就这么简单
We can turn the tide with just a breath.
咱们吹口气儿就是撒豆就成兵了
It often goes this way.
很多的时候都是这样
So when you have these abilities, you don’t need to shout slogans with others. Those who shout slogans do so out of insecurity. They need others’ support, only then do they feel their cause can succeed. Those who shout slogans,
所以当你拥有这些能力的时候 你就不需要跟别人去喊口号 喊口号的人是因为心虚 他需要别人支持 他才觉得他的事能成这喊口号的人
cough a couple of times,
咳咳咳嗽两声
thinking others won’t dare to speak up,
别人就不敢说话的人
that’s what a real leader is like.
这才是真老大
The boss has money and troops
老大是有钱有兵
having strategic buffer capabilities
有战略缓冲能力的
This is the boss
这是老大
So let me tell everyone
所以跟大家说
Don’t get caught up in grand narratives
不要陷入宏大叙事
Unless you're really studying international relations
除非你真的是学国际关系的人啊
You're truly researching international politics
你真是研究国际政治的人
You're into intelligence analysis
你是搞情报分析的人
You deal with all sorts of things
你是搞啊各种各样的
You run a consulting firm
你开咨询公司的啊
Or you run an investigative company in such cases
你开调查公司的这种情况
Or you specialize in it
或者你专门的是啊
Well, how to put it
怎么说呢
Bestselling authors in literature and history
畅销类的文史类的作者啊
You can work on these kinds of things
那你可以做这方面的东西
Or bloggers like us occasionally chat about these topics
或者像我们这些博主偶尔去聊聊这方面的事情
So let me tell you
所以我跟你讲
I really can't respect Comrade Xiaoze
哎我是真看不起小泽同志
with some of the choices he makes
他在很多上面的一些选择
I feel sorry for him
我很同情他
but pitying the weak is fatal
但是同情弱者是致命的
because in any situation
因为在任何情况下
if you pity a weak person you perpetuate their fate as the weak the weak are destined to be defeated by the strong to be absorbed The worst thing for the weak is not being defeated
你同情一个弱者 你都会延续他作为弱者的这个命运之所在 弱者注定要被强者击败 要被吸收啊 而弱者最惨的东西不是被击败
not being absorbed
不是被吸收
not being divided
不是被分化
the worst thing for the weak is being exterminated
弱者最惨的地方是被灭绝
You know he can't beat him
你明知道他打不过他
yet you arm him
你还武装他
you give him weapons
你还给他武器
you boost his confidence
给他信心
you give him something else
给他那什么
He would fight until his last drop of blood
他只有流干最后一滴血
and then still be defeated
然后还被人干掉
That's the worst outcome
这是最惨的
So, the best choice is not to resist from the start
所以一开始就不抵抗是最对的
At the beginning, you should be like Belgium
一开始你像比利时
Germany invaded
德国入境了
Stefan's plan is
史蒂芬计划嗯
Should I resist?
我要抵抗吗
After resisting, I would perish with the times
抵抗完了与时俱焚
Because often there's no need to resist at all
因为很多的时候就完全就不要抵抗
The strategies of small countries and large countries are different
小国跟大国之间的策略是不一样
If a large country doesn't resist
大国不抵抗
It will perish
大国就亡了
A small country that resists can thrive; it's that simple
小国抵抗力也王就是这么简单的事
So this is the philosophy of Social Darwinism.
所以这就是社会达尔文主义的哲学
When you have the ability to resist
你在能抵抗的时候
You need to decide whether to resist or not
你要选择抵不抵抗
And in that regard
而且来讲的话
Whether you're planning to fight or flee,
无论你是作战还是要逃跑
It's crucial to opt for negotiations at the earliest opportunity.
都要第一时间选择要和谈
Don't start by fighting from the get-go.
就一刚一开始就不要打
Don't gradually increase your troops. So you see, he initially went to attack Luhansk, and then moved on to Donetsk, sending troops bit by bit. Russia took control of Crimea, but even after taking Crimea, they didn't understand. Actually, these are all part of the upcoming strategy.
不要逐次添加兵力 所以你看他最开始去打卢甘 施策顿涅斯克的时候啊 一点点派兵力 俄罗斯占了克米里 克米里亚了也不懂 其实这些东西都是接下来的策略
To guide others to deploy troops.
指导人家出兵
In the end, this led to losing a significant portion of their territory.
最后把打成这样失去了半壁江山
To be honest,
其实来讲
This is all because Ukraine has a large group of traitorous politicians.
这都是因为乌克兰有一大帮卖国的政治家啊
How can I put it?
怎么说呢
Sooner or later, it will end up being divided between Russia and the United States.
早晚啊他其实就是被俄美两国分食了嘛
It's that simple.
就这么简单啊
He's been played by both sides.
他就是被两方都给玩了
It was eaten
给吃了
and then digested
然后给消化了
but in reality, it's just a one-yuan dish
而真正来讲它就是一块钱菜
the real dish is Europe
真正的菜是欧洲
whether it's Russia
甭管是俄罗斯
or the United States
甭管是美国
both want to take a bite of Europe
都想吃下欧洲
looking at it now
现在来看的话
in fact, Russia and the U.S. are both aiming to take over Europe
其实来讲俄美共同把欧洲吃掉
China has also joined in.
中国也加入
This is the safest option.
这是最稳妥的
Besides the three major powers—China, the U.S., and Russia—
你们上去其实除了中美俄三强以外
the rest of you are just not up to par.
你们剩下的人都是菜
First, you don’t have nuclear weapons.
一没有核武器
Second, you don’t have vast territories.
二没有广袤的国土
Third, you don’t have a large population.
三没有巨大庞大的人口
And Russia falls short in terms of population as well.
然后俄罗斯人口这方面又差一点
So, considering all these factors, The competition between major powers is really interesting. It's like playing Civilization VI. If you play Civilization VI, no matter what you do, if you have over 600 cities, or over 2000 cities,
所以这些东西来讲 它大国之间的竞争就是很好玩 就像你玩文明六一样 你要玩文明六 甭管你怎么着 你要是有600多个城市 你要有2000多个城市
or a vast continent,
你要有特别大的一片大陆
do you think you would lose the war?
你觉得你的战争会输吗
Right?
对不对
There's no question of winning or losing between major powers
大国之间更没有输跟赢的问题
only mutual destruction
只有相互毁灭
So in this sense
所以这东西来讲的话
small countries simply can't measure up
小国家根本就不是不够看的
because, to be fair
因为来讲对
from this perspective
从这一点上来讲
You could say it's social Darwinism.
你可以说是社会达尔文主义
but we have to say
但是我们要说
I only acknowledge myself as a Machiavellian
我只承认自己是马基亚维利主义者
Because Machiavellians
因为马基亚维利主义者
rely primarily on deception and surprise attacks
主要靠的就是骗和偷袭啊
rely mainly on saying one thing and meaning another
主要靠的是口是心非
In this adult world
在这个成人世界当中
I hope that as a poor child
我希望你作为一个穷孩子
you first abandon idealism
首先要抛弃理想主义
Idealism does you no good
理想主义对你没有好处
Your particularly good and kind qualities
你的那些特别好的那些善良的东西
reserve the softest part of your heart for the truly vulnerable
把你内心里最柔软的部分留给真正的弱者
Leave the real support for those who are truly disadvantaged in society
留给真正的在社会上的弱势群体
Don't waste your sympathy on those who appear weak internationally
不要去去去同情那些国际上看起来是弱者的人
Because every ethnicity Every country has its own interests Don't waste your time On things like whether it's the Russian team or the Ukrainian team It's completely meaningless I've only talked about this issue in this episode; I haven't discussed it much before
因为每个民族 每个国家都有自己的利益 不要把你的时间消耗在啊 到底是俄罗斯队还是乌克兰队这种事情啊 没有任何意义 这个问题我也只会说这一期我之前没怎么讲过
I once mentioned this on Weibo
我之前曾经在微博的时候
We also did an episode with the background of Xiao Ze.
也带着小泽的那个背景做过一期啊
It was quite fun and entertaining.
挺好玩挺搞笑的
Then I even got a like from Mr. Lai.
然后一下还被这个赖总点赞了
But at that time,
但是那个时候来讲的话
back then,
那个时候我那个时候
I feel that so many people have died in Ukraine,
我现在觉得乌克兰死去了好多啊
civilians in the war,
战争中的平民啊
and soldiers and such,
还有士兵啊之类的
their lives are truly precious.
这些人真是生命是非常的可贵的
So, in war,
所以在战争中来讲的话
both soldiers and civilians suffer the most,
双方的士兵和平民啊都是受罪最大的人
a farmer's son runs to another place,
一个农夫的儿子跑到另外一个地方
and kills another farmer's son,
杀死了另一个农夫的儿子
that is the essence of war.
这就是战争的本质
But I also want to say,
但是我还要说啊
there's one aspect that isn't pitiful,
有一点上来讲也不可怜
Once you choose such an incompetent statesman
一旦你选择了这种无能的政治家
Once your statesman is incompetent
一旦你的政治家是无能的
Then the fate of your country has reached its end.
那你这国家的国运也就到这了
This is something the common people should reflect on.
所以这个是老百姓应该反思的
Do you really want to drag a non-political figure into this?
你到底要不要办非专业性质的政治家扯进来
So in many cases, When we look at the United States, Vance chose Trump, Bask was brought in, Many people say, This is to push for reform. But in my eyes
所以很多的时候来讲 我们看美国啊 用万斯选了特朗普啊 把巴斯克搞进来 很多人说啊 这是推动改革 但是在我的眼中看来
Human history has never been kind to non-traditional statesmen
人类历史从来就不会给非传统型政治家
How much space to work with?
多少空间发挥啊
You are a reformer
你是改革者
You are a disruptor
你是破坏者
But when it comes to establishing order
但是建立秩序来讲
it still relies on those clans
还是得要靠那些氏族
It still has to rely on those traditional statesmen
还是得要靠那些传统派的政治家
because for them
因为他们来讲
have a better understanding of how the benefits are distributed
更能明白这个利益的分配是怎么回事
understand the game of diplomacy better
更懂外交的游戏
understand politics better
更懂政治
how this game is played
这个游戏是怎么玩的
so when it comes to these things
所以这些东西来讲
it's a sophisticated form of human wisdom
是一个高级的人类的智慧的东西啊
don't underestimate it
不要轻看它
don't undervalue the power of the humanities
不要小看文科的力量
in many cases
很多的时候来讲
The more such moments arise
越是这样的时候
the more you need to understand
你越要明白
in this direction
在这个方向上
as a protector of the nation
作为一个民族的一个保护者
as a leader
作为一个首脑
you must have a wide range of strategies
你要有足够多的手段
you need to have a full hand of cards
手里有足够多的牌啊
there should be no taboos in playing your cards
不要有任何的出牌的禁忌
no restrictions whatsoever
不要有禁锢
Only at this moment can you be ruthless.
只有这个时候你心狠手辣了
You're willing to stand in the shadows.
你愿意站在阴影领里
You're willing to bear the eternal blame. Only then can the people of this era enjoy peace and prosperity. The darker you are, the more ruthless your methods, the more cunning your strategies, the happier the common folk will be.
你愿意背上千古骂名 你才能让你的啊这个时代的人民啊 得到安居乐业 你越黑暗 你的手段越残忍 你的东西呢越狡诈 其实老百姓就越幸福
The safer the common folk will be.
老百姓就越安全
Because these things are directed at your enemies.
因为你这些东西是冲着敌人用
These things are aimed at hostile nations.
你的这些东西是冲着敌国啊
At adversarial forces.
敌对的东西用
So who is your enemy?
那谁是你的敌人呢
That depends on the situation.
那就看情况
We need to make as many friends as possible.
要把我们的朋友搞得多多的
We need to make as few enemies as possible.
要把我们的敌人搞得少少的啊
Only against the most stubborn enemies
只有在最顽固的敌人
should the strongest measures be used to concentrate all efforts to eliminate them.
才用最强力的手段去集中力量去消灭
But most of the time, it's about uniting and making friends.
但是平时更多的时候是要去统战的
It's about building alliances.
是要去交朋友的
Diplomacy,
Diplomacy
it's all about making friends.
All about making friends
It's that simple.
就这么简单
How to win friends and influence people.
How to win friends and influence people
That's a quote from Carnegie.
这是卡耐基的话
How to win friends,
how to win friends啊
how to gain more support,
怎么样获得更多拨号
and influence others.
and influence people和影响他人
You should read Carnegie's books.
卡耐基的书要读啊
Don't be afraid to become a cunning and crafty person.
不要害怕自己变成一个阴险狡诈的人
Because your cunning and craftiness are just on the surface,
因为你阴险狡诈的是你的外表
they are just your methods. Your appearance won't change, your mindset won't change. You might appear fierce and intimidating, but in reality, you still donate to children with disabilities, you still show your love for firefighters who sacrifice their lives for this world.
是你的手段 你的面相并不会变 你的心境并不会变 你表面上张牙舞爪 但实际上你还是会给残疾儿童捐款 你实际上还会去为这世界上牺牲的消防员啊
That makes you a truly good person.
去献上一份你的爱心
It's not about what we say,
这样来讲你就是真的好人
we judge by actions, not intentions.
而不是在于啊
Often, it's not about the strategies you adopt on the surface,
咱们说的话
or if you say something a bit too much.
君子论迹不论心
In this world,
很多的时候来讲
your survival is the most important thing.
不是在于你表面上采取什么样的策略
If you can't even survive,
你说了两句过头的话就怎么样
then nothing else matters.
所以在这个世界上
So to survive, you must use any means necessary.
只有你自己生存下来是最重要的
To survive,
如果你生存都生存不下来
to develop,
那一切都没有意义
sometimes you have to violate some principles
所以为了生存就要不择手段
that you've always believed to be right.
为了生存
Because in this world, things work by taking advantage when possible.
为了发展
As a child of an ordinary family,
有的时候就要违背一些
as someone from the lower strata of society,
内心里边儿一直觉得是对的准则
you often have to abide by the rules of society,
因为来讲天下之事
you're expected to bear the cost of everything,
顺手逆取
you're expected to follow all the rules,
你作为一个普通老百姓的孩子
but who shares the cake with you?
作为一个底层人
In fact, you are the one who should least adhere to the rules.
你很多东西来讲
The world tells us that weak countries have no diplomacy,
你都是要遵守这社会
but don't forget who the weak countries are.
全让你去背负你的代价
In this society,
然后让你去遵守一切的规则
who are the weak?
可是谁又把蛋糕分给了你呢
Aren't you just like Zelensky yourself?
其实你是最不应该去守规矩的人
What choices do you have? Before you become strong, what choices do you have? You can play them around,
这个世界告诉我们很多弱国无外交 但是不要忘了谁是弱国呀 在这个社会上 谁才是弱者呀
you can make them hate you,
你不也就是泽连斯基本人吗
they can eliminate you,
你有什么选择
or replace you.
在你变得强大之前
So use people to your advantage,
你有什么选择啊
don't act on impulse.
你可以把他们玩的团团转
That's it.
你可以让他们去恨你
So to speak,
然后消灭你
children from poor and honest families,
取代你都可以
idealism will harm you,
所以借机用人
just like it did to Zelensky.
很多的时候不要轻易的去意气用事
You need to truly become cunning and crafty,
就是这样
under
所以来讲的话